Cookery mss., circa 1660-circa 1890 LMC 2435
Lilly Library
Cookery mss.
circa 1660-circa 1918
Lilly Library
LMC 2435
61 Items
The Cookery mss., circa 1660–circa 1918, consists of bound and individual writings, often on the topic of cookery, of persons involved with cooking by practice or trade.
Access Restrictions
This collection is open for research.
Many collections are housed offsite; retrieval requires advance notice. Please make an appointment a minimum of one week in advance of your visit.
Biographical Note
Various donors.
Arrangement
Organized into the following series: I. Chesbrough; II. Additional Receipt Books.
Scope and Content Note
The Chesbrough series consists of items donated by Mary Mott Chesbrough, an editor of the Chicago Record Cook Book, originally published in 1896. The Additional Receipt Books series contains an array of receipt books and related materials. Early American cookery is represented in receipt books by Mary Hudson, Mary (Joyce) Lewis, and Edward Bradford, among others. Mexican cookery of the same era is found in two receipt books by Maria Nicolasa Maldonado and Maria F. Seventeenth century French receipts may be found in works by Jacques Vontent and Pierre Petit. French recipes or instruction books from later periods by various persons are also included. A number of English and American receipt books and individual recipes, ranging from the 18th to 19th centuries are available, by a variety of persons. A 19th century German receipt book by Christiane Schmiedling is included. Works produced in the context of the cookery trade include those by Edward Kidder the pastry maker, C. Underwood the butcher, the Cheesemakers' Guild, Corcellet the food merchant, and Alexis Benôit Soyer, a celebrated chef.
In the Additional Receipt Books series, the majority of the items are receipt books in which a cook records his or her instructions for preparing food and occasionally medicine. Menus are sometimes included within the receipt books, though this collection also contains a book of menus for dinners attended and given by Lt. General Sir Hope Grant. On occasion, individual receipts and menus are found. While the majority of the receipt books are authored by one cook, some are compilations written by several cooks. Statutes, purchasing records, and receipts produced by those involved in the cookery trade are incorporated. The visiting book of Alexis Benôit Soyer, is another part of the collection, as well as a receipt book from the library of Henry Frederick, Prince of Wales.
Note on Indexing Term - "Medicine": Many of the items contain recipes for medicines, other home-made remedies, formulae and prescriptions.
For digitized content, see Digital Collections.
Acquisition Information
Acquired: 1987-2011.
Cookbooks; Cooking; Carving (Meat, etc.) --Early works to 1800.; Home economics --Accounting.; Medicine --Early works to 1800.; Medicine; Women; Cooking, American; Cooking, German; Cooking, English; Cooking, French; Cooking, Mexican; Chesbrough, Mary Mott; Chicago record cook book.. Chesbrough, Mary Mott.
- I. Chesbrough. (Box 1)
  - Recipes of Minnie Bennett, 1835 (Box 1)
  - Recipes and menus, 1888-1900 (Box 1)
  - Recipes and menu, 1893 - 1902-3 (Box 1)
  - Recipes of Ella (Brainerd) Whitlock, 1896, Dec. 17 (Box 1)
  - Recipes and menus, 1896 - 1917 (Box 1)
  - Recipes and menus, Undated. (Box 1)
  - Recipes and menus, Undated. (Box 1)
  - Printed. Clippings of columns by M.M. Chesbrough (Box 1)
  - Printed. Miscellaneous clippings (Box 1)
- II. Additional Receipt Books.
  General
  Includes both bound and unbound materials.
  - Joyce, Mary (Lewis). Receipt book, 1776-1826 (Box 3)
  - Hudson, Mary. Receipt book (separate leaves), 1779-1838 (Box 3)
  - Joyce, Mary (Lewis). Receipt book (paid laid on), 1776-1826 (Box 3)
  - Neilson, Lockhart, 19th century. (Box 4)
  - Receipt book, 18th century. (Box 4)
  - Receipt book, 19th century. (Box 4)
  - Bradford, Edward. Cookery and household receipts, 18th-19th centuries. (Box 4)
  - Receipt book, 19th century. (Box 4)
  - Memorie de ce que jay fourni pour Monsieru Ferrier (An account of the food supplied for the wedding of M. de Ferrier), Circa 1580 (Box No Box)
  - Frederick, Henry, Prince of Wales. Receipts (bound), Circa 1610 (Box No Box)
  - Petit, Pierre, 1650 (Box No Box)
  - Vontet, Jacques, 1650 (Box No Box)
  - Powell, Elizabeth; Andrew, Tomasine, 1688-1713 (Box No Box)
  - Lady Anderson, 1690 (1660) (Box No Box)
  - Macies Book, 1691 (Box No Box)
  - Christening feast, 1696 (Box No Box)
  - Maynard, Elizabeth, 1696 (Box No Box)
  - Dashwood, Dorothea (Read). Receipts, Confectionary, etc., 1718 (Box No Box)
  - E.Kidder's receipts of pastry and coookery for the use of his scholars, Circa 1725 (Box No Box)
  - Interrogazioni da farsi alli Putti che vorrano essere ascritti Confratelli Nell'Arte nostra de formaggieri (Statutes of the Cheesemakers' Guild) (bound), 1761 (Box No Box)
  - Gerry, Samuel. Songbook and receipt book, 1767, Feb 27 (Box No Box)
  - F, Maria. [Mexican Cookbook]., Circa 1770 (Box No Box)
  - Early American Receipt book, 1770 - 1812 (Box No Box)
  - Etat et Mena General de la Dispense, 1773 (Box No Box)
  - Lady Bradshaigh & others, 1779 (Box No Box)
  - Hudson, Mary. Receipt book, 1779-1838 (Box No Box)
  - Seward, Anna. Receipt book, 1786 (Box No Box)
  - Receipt book, 1789-1809 (Box No Box)
  - Maldonado, Maria Nicolasa, 1794 (Box No Box)
  - Clothing Worsted Stocking Feet Spinning School Receipt book, 1799-1800 (Box No Box)
  - Reciepts [sic], 18th century. (Box No Box)
  - Sistême Complet de Distillation, 18th century. (Box No Box)
  - Receipt book (bound), 18th century. (Box No Box)
  - Complete transcription in unknown hand of François Marin, Les Dons de Comus ou les Délices de la Table, 18th century. (Box No Box)
  - Receipts (bound), 19th century. (Box No Box)
  - Receipts (bound), 19th century. (Box No Box)
  - Miss Tyndale, Her book, 1806 (Box No Box)
  - Chartsworth, Mary Ann, 1826 May, 30 (Box No Box)
  - Corcellet, food merchant. Bill for food items supplied to the Countess de Volager, 1831, Feb. 28 (Box No Box)
  - Alexis Benôit Soyer, cook, author. Visiting book., 1841-1857 (Box No Box)
  - Schmiedling, Christiane, 1845 (Box No Box)
  - Underwood, C, butcher. Butcher's receipt book, 1859, Dec. 21-1863, Oct. 24 (Box No Box)
  - Receipt book, including recipes for food, drink, medicine, and cosmetics. From Kovaszna Transylvnia. In Latin, German, and Hungarian, 1864 (Box No Box)
  - Grant, Lt. Gen. Sir James Hope. Menu book, 1874, June 26-1877 July 5 (Box No Box)
  - Recipe for Boston sausages, 1877, Oct. 29 (Box No Box)
  - Les dix Livres d'Apicius Coelius de la Chose Culinaire translated by Guégan, 1918 (Box No Box)
  - Calley, Isabella. Her Resaite Book, Undated. (Box No Box)
  - Receipts (bound), Undated. (Box No Box)
  - Receipt book, Undated. (Box No Box)
  - Recipes for "Le Progres" and "Profiteralles au chocolat", Undated. (Box No Box)
  - Letter from Aunt Bell to My dear Sale, includes recipe for India relish, Undated. (Box No Box)
  - 3 Receipts:. To make 8 Gallons Small Beer; Undated. To take off Sun Burn; Undated. Currant Wine, 1829, July 17 (Box No Box)
  - Bourgade, Armand. La poule son utilite et sa vie depuis sa sortie de l'oeuf jusqu'a la broche, 1885
    Scope and Contents
    Collage, ink drawing, and watercolor on card stock. Manuscript for children's book about the life of a chicken, from egg to the kitchen, written in verse